<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "doc.dtd">
<doc title="{[project]}" subtitle="Frequently Asked Questions" toc="y">
    <description>{[project]} Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ).</description>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <p>Frequently Asked Questions are intended to provide details for specific questions that may or may not be covered in the User Guide, Configuration, or Command reference. If you are unable to find details for your specific issue here, remember that the <backrest/> <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues">Issues List in GitHub</link> is also a valuable resource.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="timeout">
        <title>What if I get the <quote>could not find WAL segment</quote> error?</title>

        <p>The cause of this error can be a result of many different issues, some of which may be:</p>
        <list>
            <list-item>misconfigured archive_command</list-item>
            <list-item>misconfigured <backrest/> configuration files</list-item>
            <list-item>network or permissions issue</list-item>
            <list-item>third party product (e.g. S3, Swift or Minio) configuration issue</list-item>
            <list-item>large amount of WAL queueing to be archived</list-item>
        </list>

        <p>It is advisable to:</p>
        <list>
            <list-item>check the archive_command in <postgres/></list-item>
            <list-item>check the <backrest/> configuration settings on each host (e.g. pg* settings are set on the repository host and repo* settings on the pg host)</list-item>
            <list-item>run the <cmd>check</cmd> command with <br-setting>{[dash]}-archive-timeout</br-setting> set to a higher value than in the <backrest/> configuration file (or default) to see if the WAL queue needs more time to clear. If the system is generating a lot of WAL, then consider configuring <link url="https://pgbunker.github.io/website/user-guide.html#async-archiving">asynchronous archiving</link></list-item>
        </list>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="manual-expire">
        <title>How do I manually purge a backup set?</title>

        <p>A full backup set can be expired using the <br-setting>{[dash]}-set</br-setting> option as explained in <link url="https://pgbunker.github.io/website/command.html#command-expire">Command Reference: Expire</link>.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="optimize-config">
        <title>How can I configure options independently for each command?</title>

        <p><backrest/> has the ability to set options independently in the configuration file for each command. <link url="https://pgbunker.github.io/website/user-guide.html#quickstart/configure-stanza">Configure Cluster Stanza</link> details this feature as well as option precedence.</p>
        <p>For example, the <br-option>process-max</br-option> option can be optimized for each command:</p>

        <code-block>
[global]
# used where not overridden
process-max=2

[global:backup]
# more cores for backup
process-max=4

[global:restore]
# all the cores for restore
process-max=8

[global:archive-push]
# more cores for archive-push
process-max=3

[global:archive-get]
# fewer cores for archive-get
process-max=1
        </code-block>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="s3-bucket">
        <title>Can I use dots (periods) in my S3 bucket name?</title>

        <p><proper>RFC-2818</proper> does not allow wildcards to match on a dot (.) so s3 bucket names must not contain dots. If there are dots in the S3 bucket name then an error such as <quote>unable to find hostname 'my.backup.bucket.s3.amazonaws.com' in certificate common name or subject alternative names</quote> will occur.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="old-package">
        <title>Where can I find packages for older versions of <backrest/>?</title>

        <p>The <link url="https://apt.postgresql.org">apt.postgresql.org</link> repository maintains an <link url="https://apt-archive.postgresql.org">archive of older versions</link>. Debian also maintains <link url="https://snapshot.debian.org/binary/pgbackrest/">snapshots</link> of all test builds.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="backup-standby">
        <title>Why does a backup attempt fail when <br-option>backup-standby=y</br-option> and the standby database is down?</title>

        <p>Configuring backup from standby is generally intended to reduce load on the primary, so switching backups to the primary when the standby is down often defeats the point. Putting more load on the primary in a situation where there are already failures in the system is not recommended. Backups are not critical as long as you have one that is fairly recent -- the important thing is to keep up with WAL archiving. There is plenty of time to get a backup when the system is stable again.</p>

        <p>If you really need a backup, the solution is to have more standbys or remove <br-option>backup-standby</br-option>. This can be overridden on the command line with <br-option>--no-backup-standby</br-option>, so there is no need to reconfigure for a one-off backup.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="standby-repo">
        <title>Should I setup my repository on a standby host?</title>

        <p>No. When primary and standby databases are configured, the <backrest/> configuration files should be symmetric in order to seamlessly handle failovers. If they are not, the configurations will need to be changed on failover or further problems may result.</p>

        <p>See the <link url="user-guide.html#repo-host">Dedicated Repository Host</link> section of the <proper>User Guide</proper> for more information.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="time-based-pitr">
        <title>Time-based Point-in-Time Recovery does not appear to work, why?</title>

        <p>The most common mistake when using time-based Point-in-Time Recovery is forgetting to choose a backup set that is before the target time. <backrest/> will attempt to discover a backup to play forward from the time specified by the <setting>--target=</setting> if the <setting>--set</setting> option is not specified. If a backup set cannot be found, then restore will default to the latest backup. However, if the latest backup is after the target time, then <setting>--target=</setting> is not considered valid by <postgres/> and is therefore ignored, resulting in WAL recovery to the latest time available.</p>

        <p>To use the <setting>--set</setting> option, choose a backup set by running the <cmd>info</cmd> command and finding the backup with a timestamp stop that is before the target time. Then when running the restore, specify the option <setting>--set=BACKUP_LABEL</setting> where <id>BACKUP_LABEL</id> is the chosen backup set.</p>

        <p>See the <link url="user-guide.html#pitr">Point-in-Time Recovery</link> section of the <proper>User Guide</proper> for more information.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <!--
        At least these issues have been asking about this:
            https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/1485
            https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/1663
    -->
    <section id="archive-suffix">
        <title>What does the WAL archive suffix mean?</title>

        <p>The suffix is the SHA1 checksum used to verify file integrity. There is no way to omit it.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="restore-speed">
        <title>Does it take longer to restore specific backup types (full, differential, incremental)?</title>

        <p>The various backup types require the same amount of time to restore. Restore retrieves files based on the backup manifest, which may reference files from a previous backup in the case of incremental or differential backups. While there could be differences in time spent <i>making</i> a given backup (depending on backup type), database size determines restore time (disk I/O, network I/O, etc. being equal).</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="self-contained-backup">
        <title>How can I export a backup for use in a network-isolated environment?</title>

        <p><backrest/> uses the repository not only to store backups and WAL archives but also to maintain essential metadata required for features such as compression, encryption, and file bundling. Because of this, simply copying a backup along with a subset of WAL files usually will not work unless very specific and restrictive conditions are met.</p>

        <p>However, there is a workaround if your goal is to create a self-contained export of a database that you can transfer (e.g., via USB). You can make a backup with the <link url="https://pgbunker.github.io/website/command.html#command-backup/category-command/option-archive-copy">--archive-copy</link> option enabled to ensure that the necessary WAL segments are stored along with the backup. Then, restore it using <link url="https://pgbunker.github.io/website/command.html#command-restore/category-command/option-type">--type=none</link> --pg1-path=/your/target/path. This produces a restored PostgreSQL data directory with all required WAL files already placed in <code>pg_wal</code>, similar to what <file>pg_basebackup</file> would create.</p>

        <p>You can then copy this directory to another system, and <postgres/> should be able to recover from it without needing access to the <backrest/> repository.</p>

        <p>Please note that recovering this backup will not result in a timeline switch, which means that this cluster should not push WAL to the original repository that it was exported from. If the new cluster is in a network-isolated environment this should not be a problem.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="wsl-support">
        <title>Does <backrest/> work on Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL)?</title>

        <p><backrest/> is not officially tested on WSL, and no WSL-specific testing matrix is maintained. However, since WSL runs supported Linux distributions, the upstream maintainer's view is that it should work in practice. There are no known WSL-specific blockers documented. If running on WSL is impractical for your environment, third-party container images of <backrest/> exist as an alternative (these are community-maintained and not officially provided by the project).</p>

        <p>See <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2725">upstream issue #2725</link> for the original discussion.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="repo-cmd-stanza">
        <title>Why does <br-option>--stanza</br-option> seem to have no effect on <cmd>repo-ls</cmd> and <cmd>repo-get</cmd>?</title>

        <p>The <br-option>--stanza</br-option> option is honored by <cmd>repo-ls</cmd> and <cmd>repo-get</cmd>, but those commands take a repository-relative path rather than constructing one from the stanza. To list a stanza's archive directory, supply the path explicitly:</p>

        <code-block>
pgbackrest --stanza=demo repo-ls archive/demo
        </code-block>

        <p>Internal storage path macros such as <code>&lt;REPO:ARCHIVE&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;REPO:BACKUP&gt;</code> exist in the source, but they are not part of the documented interface and are not guaranteed to remain stable across versions. Most users find that supplying the explicit relative path is clearer and more reliable.</p>

        <p>See <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2735">upstream issue #2735</link> for context.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="direct-io">
        <title>Does <backrest/> use direct I/O to avoid polluting the OS page cache during large backups?</title>

        <p><backrest/> does not use direct I/O. Backups are dominated by sequential reads, and the upstream maintainer has noted that the kernel's read-ahead handles that workload well, so mechanisms like <code>io_uring</code> were judged to add significant complexity without proportional benefit.</p>

        <p>To mitigate page cache pollution from large repository writes, <backrest/> calls <code>posix_fadvise(POSIX_FADV_DONTNEED)</code> on posix repository files after writing, prompting the kernel to drop those pages. This change comes from upstream <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/pull/2758">PR #2758</link> and is present in pgBunker as a cherry-pick.</p>

        <p>See <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2727">upstream issue #2727</link> for the original discussion.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="rpm-logrotate-permission">
        <title>Why does <file>logrotate</file> fail with permission errors after an RPM update?</title>

        <p>The PGDG RPM packages install <file>/etc/logrotate.d/pgbackrest</file> with the <id>postgres</id> user to align with PostgreSQL conventions. However, the recommended deployment for dedicated repository hosts uses a separate <id>pgbackrest</id> user (matching the default <br-option>repo-host-user</br-option> setting). When the package's logrotate configuration runs against files owned by <id>pgbackrest</id>, permission errors result.</p>

        <p>The upstream-recommended workaround is to change ownership after the first package installation:</p>

        <code-block>
chown -R pgbackrest:pgbackrest /var/log/pgbackrest /var/lib/pgbackrest
        </code-block>

        <p>Subsequent package upgrades will preserve those ownership changes, just as they preserve modified configuration files. Alternatively, override <file>/etc/logrotate.d/pgbackrest</file> with a custom configuration matching the user that actually owns the log files.</p>

        <p>See <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2737">upstream issue #2737</link> for context.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="server-tls-server-auth">
        <title>Why do I get <quote>option 'tls-server-auth' must be set</quote> when I am not using the <cmd>server</cmd> command?</title>

        <p>The <cmd>server</cmd> command is a TLS-based daemon used as an alternative to SSH for remote operations. Most deployments using SSH transport or direct repository access never invoke it. This command requires <br-setting>tls-server-auth</br-setting> by design, because TLS authentication is mandatory for that protocol.</p>

        <p>If you encounter this error without intentionally configuring TLS, a systemd unit installed by your distribution package is likely starting the server in the background. List candidate units, then disable any that you do not need (substituting the actual unit name):</p>

        <code-block>
systemctl list-units | grep pgbackrest
systemctl disable --now pgbackrest.service
        </code-block>

        <p>See <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2756">upstream issue #2756</link> for context.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="remote-env-vars">
        <title>Why are environment variables not honored by remote <backrest/> processes?</title>

        <p>Options that contain secrets (for example, S3 credentials) are deliberately not passed from the originating host to remote processes via the command line, because doing so would expose them in <cmd>ps</cmd> output and other process listings. As a consequence, environment variables set only on the host invoking <cmd>backup</cmd> do not reach the remote PostgreSQL or repository host.</p>

        <p>Set the relevant variables on the remote host itself, using one of:</p>
        <list>
            <list-item>The user's shell profile (e.g. <file>~/.bash_profile</file>) on the remote host.</list-item>
            <list-item>The systemd unit that launches <backrest/> on the remote host.</list-item>
            <list-item>SSH <code>SendEnv</code> on the client and <code>AcceptEnv</code> on the remote, to forward specific variables across the SSH connection.</list-item>
            <list-item>Storing the credentials directly in <file>pgbackrest.conf</file> on the remote host, where they will not appear in process listings.</list-item>
        </list>

        <p>See <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2733">upstream issue #2733</link> for context.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="client-state-error">
        <title>What does <quote>client state is 'X' but expected 'idle'</quote> (error 039) mean?</title>

        <p>This error is almost always a secondary symptom of an underlying failure that disrupted the protocol state machine, not a primary <backrest/> bug. Common root causes include exhausted disk space, an OOM kill of a subprocess, an unrelated subprocess crash, or noise on the SSH connection corrupting the protocol stream.</p>

        <p>To find the real error, rerun the failing command with verbose subprocess logging:</p>

        <code-block>
pgbackrest --log-level-file=debug --log-subprocess=y --stanza=demo backup
        </code-block>

        <p>Then inspect the per-subprocess log files (for example, files named like <file>demo-backup-local-001.log</file>) for the original error that preceded the state mismatch. It is also worth checking <cmd>dmesg</cmd> for OOM kills and verifying that the repository and PGDATA filesystems still have free space.</p>

        <p>If the failures correlate with SSH transport, consider switching to the TLS-based remote protocol, which is less prone to state corruption from transport-layer noise.</p>

        <p>See <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2729">upstream issue #2729</link> and <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2744">upstream issue #2744</link> for context.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <section id="azure-mi-aks-multi-identity">
        <title>Why does Azure Managed Identity authentication fail on AKS nodes with multiple identities?</title>

        <p>When <br-option>repo-azure-key-type=auto</br-option> is configured, <backrest/> obtains an access token from the Azure Instance Metadata Service (IMDS). On AKS nodes that have more than one user-assigned managed identity attached, IMDS refuses the unqualified request and returns a message such as:</p>

        <code-block>
Multiple user assigned identities exist, please specify the clientId / resourceId of the identity in the token request
        </code-block>

        <p><backrest/> does not currently expose a configuration option to select a specific managed identity in this case. Available workarounds:</p>
        <list>
            <list-item>Switch to <br-option>repo-azure-key-type=shared</br-option> or <br-option>repo-azure-key-type=sas</br-option> and supply credentials explicitly.</list-item>
            <list-item>Reconfigure the AKS node so that only one managed identity is relevant for the storage account in use.</list-item>
        </list>

        <p>See <link url="https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/2741">upstream issue #2741</link> for context.</p>
    </section>

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <!-- <section id="different-server">
        <title>How to restore a backup to a different server (for example, a production backup to a development server)?</title>

        <p>It is often desirable to restore the latest backup from a production server to a development server. In principal, the instructions are the same as in <link url="https://pgbunker.github.io/website/user-guide.html#replication/hot-standby">setting up a hot standby</link> with a few exceptions.</p>

        <p>NEED TO ELABORATE HERE: Need an example of the restore command - what settings are different? Would they be {[dash]}-target, {[dash]}-target-action=promote, {[dash]}-type=immediate on the command-line? What about in the POSTGRES (e.g. hot_standby = on / wal_level = hot_standby - these would be different, no?) and PGBACKREST (e.g. would recovery-option=standby_mode=on still be set?) config files</p>
    </section> -->

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <!-- <section id="minio">
        <title>Setting up Minio for pgBunker</title>

        <p>Setting up Minio for pgBunker https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/645/</p>
    </section> -->

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <!-- <section id="patroni">
        <title>Patroni</title>

        <p>Patroni: https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/702</p>
    </section> -->

    <!-- ======================================================================================================================= -->
    <!-- <section id="SOMETHING">
        <title>SOMETHING</title>

        <p>Issue 610 - has come up a couple times, so distill it and point to this as a resource https://github.com/pgbackrest/pgbackrest/issues/610</p>
    </section> -->
</doc>
